<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Daniel Menéndez Crespo</title>
    <link>https://zyth0s.github.io/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://zyth0s.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 16:37:15 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://zyth0s.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://zyth0s.github.io/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientific Memes</title>
      <link>https://zyth0s.github.io/post/scientific-memes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 16:37:15 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zyth0s.github.io/post/scientific-memes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Science is an indisputable source of progress for our society. A topical
example is the use of recent advances in biochemistry to foster new vaccines
for Sars-CoV-19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The compendium of acquired scientific knowledge is so vast that nobody is
expected to be illustrated in every branch of science, not even a field or
subfield. For that reason it is difficult to even be aware of the main
questions, concepts or definitions addressed currently by almost any
discipline. In this regard, it would be helpful if we had at our disposal a
collection of brief descriptions for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we seek to condense in the least amount of words, images, or recording
length a given concept in science.  Much like memes in Dawkins&#39; description of
the term (and contrary to popular usage) scientific memes are meant to be
&lt;em&gt;units of scientific information, such as a scientific concept or question,
that are transmitted verbally or visually from one mind to another&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you might ask how should those memes be. Something like a dictionary entry?
Quite not. We would like a more rich medium, with some illustration to it.  A
very good example is the following &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.i-programmer.info/programming/theory/3758-understanding-the-fourier-transform.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;explanation of Fourier transform by Stuart
Riffle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;fourier_transform.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same format has been used to explain other mathematical concepts (examples
taken from &lt;a href=&#34;https://betterexplained.com/articles/colorized-math-equations/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Better
explained&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;euler_number.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;euler_formula.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A not less impressive format is used by physics professor &lt;a href=&#34;https://bunim180.wixsite.com/jurij0001&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Yuri
Kovalenok&lt;/a&gt;. The following is only an
example of a large collection of notebook notes handwritten by Yuri&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;rocket.webp&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More like that by twitter user &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;@ThuyNganVu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;quadratic.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those notes are based on videos recorded by Youtube user
&lt;a href=&#34;http://youtube.com/c/3blue1brown&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;3blue1brown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am pretty sure there are more examples like those around but those are the
ones I encountered. Often when I learn a new concept I try to leave a note for myself that
helps me when I forget what is the meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Umklapp process: part of the momentum that the neutron gives to the solid
goes to the centre of mass of the solid. The other part transforms into
phonon modes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anderson &amp;amp; Kondo? Is the hybridisation of strongly correlated electron states
with free electron bands. The problem is how to hybridise states of
completely different nature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pierls instability is like the resonance in poly-acetylene between
alternating bonds. The system spontaneously dimerises in two resonant ground
state configurations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bloch states are closely related to chemists resonant structure concept&lt;/em&gt;
“Modern Cond matter physics book”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spin-orbit coupling: &lt;em&gt;Physically it can be understood as the Zeeman coupling
between the magnetic moment carried by electron spin and the effective
magnetic field seen by the electron in the reference frame in which it is at
rest, while the other charges move around it&lt;/em&gt; “Modern Condensed matter Physics
book”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oxidation state: is the formal charge minus electrons shared with less
electronegative atoms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Josephson junction – &lt;em&gt;a non-superconducting region through which the Cooper
pairs responsible for superconductivity can tunnel. This semiconducting “weak
link” provides a persistent phase difference between the superconductors in the
circuit, similar to the way that a classical battery provides a persistent
voltage drop in an electronic circuit. Thanks to this phase difference, a
superconducting current (that is, a current with zero dissipation) flows when
the junction is embedded in the superconducting circuit&lt;/em&gt; Featured in Physics
World&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here’s an extremely brief version of the black hole information paradox:
Stuff falls into a black hole. Over time — a long, long time — the black hole
“evaporates.” What happened to the stuff? According to the rules of gravity,
it’s gone, its information lost forever. But according to the rules of quantum
mechanics, information can never be lost. Therefore, paradox.&lt;/em&gt; Featured in
Quanta magazine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The biggest puzzle in cosmology right now has to do with the Hubble
constant, a measure of the speed at which the universe is expanding. Data
from the early universe predicts one value. Data from the modern universe
predicts another.&lt;/em&gt; Featured in Quanta magazine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/M7OW1BYT1R?amp=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hawking radiation by Gaston Giribet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spectral decomposition with Julia</title>
      <link>https://zyth0s.github.io/post/spectral-decomposition-with-julia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 11:26:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zyth0s.github.io/post/spectral-decomposition-with-julia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We briefly discuss how to eigendecompose a symmetric square matrix, and check some of its properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note about notation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vectors are bold lowercase, like $\mathbf{u,v}$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;matrices are bold uppercase, like $\mathbf{A,B,C}$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scalars are lowercase, like $x,y,z$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&#39;&lt;/code&gt; means (i) the complex conjugate for scalars, or (ii) the (conjugate) transpose for vectors/matrices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-julia&#34;&gt;using LinearAlgebra: eigen, Diagonal, I, det, rank
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given an ordered basis every linear mapping has a unique transformation matrix.
A way to characterize the matrix representation of the linear mapping is by how
it transforms vectors. It turns out that we can find a set of special vectors
that are just scaled by some &lt;em&gt;eigenvalue&lt;/em&gt; when we apply the linear mapping to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets take a $4 \times 4$ matrix,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-julia&#34;&gt;A = rand(4,4)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that is symmetric (or hermitic if elements were complex)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-julia&#34;&gt;A = (A + A&#39;)/2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A $4 \times 4$ matrix has 4 eigenvalues $(e_1,e_2,e_3,e_4)$
and 4 respective eigenvectors $(\mathbf{v}_1,\mathbf{v}_2,\mathbf{v}_3,\mathbf{v}_4)$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-julia&#34;&gt;e, U = eigen(A) # solves $Av = ev$
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;eigen&lt;/code&gt; returns the eigenvalues in a vector &lt;code&gt;e&lt;/code&gt; and
the eigenvectors as columns of a matrix &lt;code&gt;U&lt;/code&gt;.
E.g. the first eigenvalue is $e_1 =$ &lt;code&gt;e[1]&lt;/code&gt; and the first
eigenvector is $\mathbf{v}_1 =$ &lt;code&gt;U[:,1]&lt;/code&gt;.
Note that eigenvalues are ordered in descending order and eigenvectors
reflect this reordering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can check that the secular equation $|\mathbf{A} - e_i\mathbf{I}| = 0$ is satisfied (for each eigenvalue)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-julia&#34;&gt;for i in 1:4
   isapprox( det(A - e[i]*I), 0.00, atol=1e-4) || error(&amp;quot;Secular equation $i not satisfied&amp;quot;)
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The corresponding eigenvectors satisfy $(\mathbf{A} - e_i\mathbf{I})\mathbf{v} = \mathbf{0}$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-julia&#34;&gt;for i in 1:4
   isapprox( (A - e[i]*I)*U[:,i], fill(0.00,4), atol=1e-4) || error(&amp;quot;a) Eigenvalue equation $i not satisfied&amp;quot;)
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or equivalently $\mathbf{A}\mathbf{v} = e_i\mathbf{v}$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-julia&#34;&gt;for i in 1:4
   isapprox( A*U[:,i], e[i]*U[:,i], atol=1e-4) || error(&amp;quot;b) Eigenvalue equation $i not satisfied&amp;quot;)
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If $\mathbf{A}$ is symmetric, thus $\mathbf{U}$ is orthonormal and $\mathbf{U}&#39; = \mathbf{U}^{-1}$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If $\mathbf{A}$ is hermitic, thus $\mathbf{U}$ is unitary and $\mathbf{U}&#39; = \mathbf{U}^{-1}$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cases it can be described as a similarity transformation
$$ \mathbf{A} = \mathbf{U} \mathbf{D} \mathbf{U}^{-1} = \mathbf{U} \mathbf{D} \mathbf{U}&#39; $$
where $\mathbf{D}$ is a diagonal matrix with the eigenvalues as diagonal elements.
Therefore, $\mathbf{D}$ is the matrix that diagonalizes $\mathbf{A}$.
$\mathbf{A}$ and $\mathbf{D}$ are said to be similar matrices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-julia&#34;&gt;A ≈ U * Diagonal(e) * U&#39; || error(&amp;quot;Not a similarity transformation&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similarity transformation is also a conformal mapping. A matrix $\mathbf{W}$
encoding a crystallographic symmetry operation is an isometry if
$$ \mathbf{G} \approx \mathbf{W} \mathbf{G} \mathbf{W}&#39; $$
where $\mathbf{G}$ is the metric tensor.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
